Finding Aid for the Political Newspapers from Buenos Aires LSC.1812
UCLA Library Special Collections
Political Newspapers from Buenos Aires
1786-1851 (bulk 1812-1851)
1812-1851
UCLA Library Special Collections
Hoffman, Olga Mingo
LSC.1812
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes, 2 oversize boxes)
This collection contains political newspapers published in Buenos Aires, Argentina from 1812 to 1851. Publications contain a range of topics with a focus on Argentine national issues but also include international news. The newspapers are primarily in Spanish, with some English, French, and Latin, beginning shortly after Argentine independence.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Olga Mingo Hoffman, gift, 1994.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9963633663606533
Scope and Content
This collection contains political newspapers published in Buenos Aires, Argentina from 1812 to 1851. The collection includes the following publications: La abeja argentina, El abogado nacional, Archivo Americano y espiritu de la prensa del mundo, El centinela, Diario de sesiones, El duende de Buenos Ayres, La gazeta de Buenos Ayres/La gaceta de Buenos Aires, La gaceta mercantil, Lucero, El Oficial del Dia, and El observador. In addition, there is one document on medical issues published in Spain and written in Latin in 1786, entitled Quaestiones medicae sortitae et lege praefixo 10 dier. Termino typis mandatae.
The collection is primarily in Spanish, with some English, French, and Latin, and cover Argentine social, political, economic, commercial, governmental, religious, and cultural issues. Researchers interested in international issues should consult El Archivo Americano y Espiritu de la Prensa del Mundo, El Abogado Nacional, La Gazeta de Buenos Ayres, and Lucero. Researchers with interest in the caudillo dictator Juan Manuel de Rosas should consult El Archivo Americano y Espiritu de la Prensa del Mundo, La Gaceta Mercantil, and Lucero. Researchers interested in Bolivar should consult El Duende de Buenos Ayres.
Coverage of news regarding Buenos Aires, both province and city, is particularly strong throughout the collection and demonstrates the many newspaper sources dating from shortly after Argentine independence through the mid-19th century.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetical by publication title and chronologically within each title.
Box 1 contains La abeja argentina, El abogado nacional, Archivo americano y espiritu de la prensa del mundo, El centinela, El duende de Buenos Ayres, La gazeta de Buenos Ayres/La gaceta de Buenos Aires, El oficial del dia, and El observador. The folders are arranged alphabetically by name of publication and chronologically within each folder.
Box 2 contains Diario de Sesiones from Buenos Aires and Rio de la Plata. They are organized by location and chronologically. Box 2 also contains the item in the Miscellaneous series, Quaestiones medicae sortitae et lege praefixo 10 dier. Termino typis mandatae.
Box 3 contains La gaceta mercantile. Each issue is in a separate folder in chronological order.
Box 4 contains the bound volume of Lucero organized in chronological order.
Newspapers.; Buenos Aires (Argentina).
- La Abeja Argentina, 1822
  Scope and Contents note
  La Abeja Argentina began publishing in 1822; the collection's run includes their premiere issue. It published articles relating to the political and economic independence of Argentina with a focus on the political and economic situation of the province of Buenos Aires.
  - La Abeja Argentina, 1822 April 15? -1822 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Number 1 (April 15?), 2 (2 copies, one with cover, May 15), 3 (June 15), 4 (July 15)
- El Abogado Nacional, 1819-1820
  El Abogado Nacional was a bi-weekly publication printed in Spanish by Imprenta de la Independencia. The collection contains four issues from January to March 1819. The first three issues contain a letter to the editor and his response. All the articles pertain to national and international politics, particularly that in Spain, the United States, and Venezuela. The last section of the publication consists of notices of items for sale. This series also contains a bonus publication released on February 19, 1820 regarding a military proclamation.
  - El Abogado Nacional, 1819 January 15 - 1820 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Numbers 5-8 (1819 January 15 - March 15), Extraordinaria (1820 February 19)
- El Archivo Americano y Espiritu de la Prensa del Mundo, 1848-1851
  El Archivo Americano y Espiritu de la Prensa del Mundo was a publication edited by Pedro de Angeles who was in favor of the dictator Juan Manuel de Rosas. It was published by Imprenta de la Independencia and contained articles, official documents, national and international news. It also includes correspondence between Rosas and British minister Sir Henry Southern. It was the most important organ for the dissemination of the ideas and policies of Rosas in the United States and Europe. Articles were published in Spanish, English and French; some are translations into Spanish.
  - El Archivo Americano y Espiritu de la Prensa del Mundo, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Number 11
  - El Archivo Americano y Espiritu de la Prensa del Mundo, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Number 17
  - El Archivo Americano y Espiritu de la Prensa del Mundo, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Number 21
  - El Archivo Americano y Espiritu de la Prensa del Mundo, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Number 22
  - El Archivo Americano y Espiritu de la Prensa del Mundo, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Appedix to number 26
- El Centinela, 1823
  The collection contains one incomplete issue of El Centinela dated February 9, 1823. The publication includes an 1822 treasury report for Buenos Aires, a letter to the editor on church reform, an article in favor of the government of Bernadino Rivadavia (1780-1845) and poetry.
  - El Centinela, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Number 28
- El Correo Judicial, 1834
  El Correo Judicial was a semi-weekly publication printed in Spanish by Imprenta de la Libertad. The collection contains seven issues published from August to October 1834. The publication was edited by jurist Bernardo Velez and contained articles on legal cases related to commerce.
  - El Correo Judicial, 1834 August 30 -October 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Number 2 (August 30), 3 (2 copies, 1834 August 30), 4 (September 17), 5 (September 25), 6 (October 4), 7 (October 11)
- Diario de Sesiones, 1822-1843
  Includes legislative journals Diario de Sesiones de la Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, Diario de Sesiones del Congreso Nacional de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata, and Diario de Sesiones del Congreso General Constituyente de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata. These journals contain the "minutes" of legislative sessions, transcriptions of debates, texts of decrees and resolutions, and cabinet reports.
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1822 May 1-September 30 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Tomo primero, bound volume
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1822 August 16 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Number ?
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1823 June 9 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Number 4
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1823 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Number 6
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1823 August 13 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1823 August 25 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Number 17, 2 copies
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1823 September 5 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    2 copies
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1823 September 17 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    2 copies, copy 2 incomplete, missing last 10 pages
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1823 October 23 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Number 24
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1830 July 7 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Number 198
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 January 19 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Number 632
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 February 15 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Number 633
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 April 6 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Number 636
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 April 8 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Number 637
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 April 10 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Number 638
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Number 639
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 April 16 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Number 640
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 April 27 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Number 641
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Number 644
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Number 645
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 June 28 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Number 646
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 July 2 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Number 647
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1839 December 28 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Number 657, Index
  - Diario de Sesiones de la H. Junta de Representantes de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, 1843 January 1-1843 December 22 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Tomo 29, number 721-729, index, bound volume
  - Diario de Sesiones del Congreso Nacional de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata en Sud America, 1824 December 6-1825 January 23 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Number 1-16, bound volume
  - Diario de Sesiones del Congreso General Constituyente de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata, 1825 July 4-1826 January 12 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Number 45-80, bound volume
  - Diario de Sesiones del Congreso General Constituyente de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata, 1826 January 19-1826 February 6 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Number 81-93, bound volume
  - Diario de Sesiones del Congreso General Constituyente de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata, 1826 April 5 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Number 113
  - Diario de Sesiones del Congreso General Constituyente de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata, 1826 April 8 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Number 115
  - Diario de Sesiones del Congreso General Constituyente de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata, 1826 April 10 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Number 116
  - Diario de Sesiones del Congreso General Constituyente de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata, 1826 October 10 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Number 210
- El Duende de Buenos Ayres, 1826
  El Duende de Buenos Ayres was a weekly newspaper that published various articles and documents on Bolivar.
  - El Duende de Buenos Ayres, 1826 December 21 - 1827 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Number 20 (1826 December 21), 21 (1827 January 6), 23 (January 25), 25 (February 7), 27-33 (February 21-April 9)
- La Gaceta Mercantil, 1827-1850
  La Gaceta Mercantil: Diario commercial, politico y literario was a daily publication running from 1823-1852. It provides a detailed glimpse into the political and commercial life of 19th century Buenos Aires as well as the literary, intellectual and cultural life of the province. It was edited by Stephen Hallet, an Irish-born printer living in Buenos Aires and includes articles, editorials, minutes of government sessions, international news, letters to the editor, poetry, ship arrivals, mail schedule, weather and time of sunrise and sunset, and announcements in Spanish and English. Announcements include help wanted, lost and found, sale, event announcements, change of address, auction and estate sales, and real estate sales. The articles are written from a strong pro-Rosas, federalist perspective The March 31, 1840 issue contains a papal letter of Gregory XVI that forbids slave trade; the letter was printed in English and Latin.
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1827 September 24 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Number 1153
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1827 September 26 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Number 1155
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1827 September 27 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Number 1156
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1827 October 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Number 1159
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1827 October 20 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Number 1175
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1827 October 22 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Number 1176
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 April 29 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Number 1324
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 June 10 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Number 1357
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 June 25 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Number 1369
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 June 26 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Number 1370
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 July 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Number 1375
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 August 12 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Number 1406
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 August 16 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Number 1410
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 August 23 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Number 1416
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 September 13 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Number 1432
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 September 15 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Number 1433
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 September 16 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Number 1434
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 September 17 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Number 1435
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 September 23 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Number 1440
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 September 24 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Number 1441
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 September 25 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Number 1442
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1828 November 10 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Number 1478
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 January 20 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Number 4459
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 January 21 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Number 4960
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 January 22 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Number 4961
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 February 10 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Number 4977
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 February 11 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Number 4978
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 February 13 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Number 4980
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 February 17 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Number 4983
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 February 19 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Number 4985
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 February 20 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Number 4986
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 March 12 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Number 5002
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 March 31 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Number 5017
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 April 13 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Number 5018
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 July 2 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Number 5019
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 August 18 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Number 5114
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 August 28 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Number 5123
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 August 31 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Number 5125
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 November 27 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Number 5195
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 December 1 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Number 5198
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 December 2 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Number 5199
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 December 11 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Number 5205
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 December 17 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Number 5201
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1846 June 22 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Number 6806
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1846 June 26 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Number 6811
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1846? June 27 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Number 6812
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1840 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Number 6813
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1846 July 1 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Number 6814
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1846 July 2 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Number 6815
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1846 July 31 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Number 6839
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1846 August 1 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Number 6840
  - La Gaceta Mercantil, 1850 May 9 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Number 7942, 2 copies
- La Gazeta de Buenos Ayres, 1812-1820
  La Gazeta de Buenos Ayres, which changed its name to La Gaceta de Buenos Aires in 1820, is the oldest run of newspapers in the collection. The series contains an incomplete run of newspapers from January 10, 1812 to June 28, 1820; the majority of the issues are from 1818 to 1820. La Gazeta de Buenos Aires was a weekly newspaper printed in Spanish by Imprenta de los Niños Expósitos, which was shortened to Imprenta de los Expositos in 1818. The articles and letters to the editor generally pertain to politics in Argentina, South America and Europe. Topics include the military exploits of Napoleon and Bolivar, the Inquisition in Spain, and political affairs in France, England, Spain, Portugal, and Chile. The end of the publication includes ship arrivals and departures and notices of items wanted and for sale. This section also includes notices on slaves that were missing and for sale.
  - La Gazeta de Buenos Ayres, 1812 January 10 - 1817 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Number 19 (1812 January 10), 41 (1816 February 3), 66 (1816 August 3), Extraordinaria (1817 February 5)
  - La Gazeta de Buenos Ayres, 1818 January 24 - 1818 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Number 55 (January 24), 56 (January 31), 57 (February 7), 58 (February 14), 60 (February 28), 61 (March 7), 62 (March 18), 63 (March 25), 64 (April 1), 65 (April 8), 66 (April 15), 68 (April 29), 69 (May 6)
  - La Gazeta de Buenos Ayres, 1819 February 3 - 1819 August 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Number 108 (February 3), 109 (February 1), 110 (February 17), 126 (June 16), 127 (June 23), 128 (June 30), 129 (July 7), 131 (July 21), 136 (August 25)
  - La Gazeta de Buenos Ayres, 1820 January 19 - June 28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Number 156 (January 19), 161 (February 23), 162 (March 1), 164 (March 15), 9 (June 28)
- El Lucero, 1833
  Lucero: Diario Politico, Literario, y Mercantil was a daily publication edited by Pedro de Angelis (1784-1859), a Neapolitan émigré who became one of Argentina's early historians. He edited and published a number of important historical documents and published Crónica política y literaria de Buenos Aires (1829), in addition to Lucero. He is often reviled by contemporary historians for his work in support of Rosas during the dictator's rule. Lucero contained national and international new, police news, official documents, general announcements, and notices of auctions and sales.
  - El Lucero, 1833 January 1 - June 28 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Number 953 (January 1), 954 (January 2), 955 (January 3), 960 (January 9), 961 (January 10), 962 (January 11), 963 (January 12), 970 (January 21), 972 (January 23), 973 (January 24), 974 (January 25), 975 (January 26), 976 (January 28), 977 (January 29), 979 (January 31), 980 (February 1), 982 (February 3), 984 (February 6), 985 (February 7), 986 (February 8), 987 (February 9), 988 (February 11), 989 (February 12), 990 (February 13), 991 (February 14), 997 (February 23), 998 (February 25), 999 (February 26), 100 (February 27), 1001 (February 28), 1002 (March 1), 1003 (March 2), 1004 (March 4), 1005 (March 5), 1006 (March 6), 1007 (March 7), 1008 (March 8), 1009 (March 9), 1010 (March 11), 1011 (March 12), 1012 (March 13), 1013 (March 14), 1014 (March 15), 1015 (March 16), 1016 (March 18), 1017 (March 19), 1018 (March 20), 1019 (March 21), 1020 (March 22), 1021 (March 23), 1023 (March 27), 1023 (March 27), 1024 (March 28), 1025 (March 29), 1027 (April 1), 1028 (April 2), 1029 (April 3), 1030 (April 8), 1031 (April 9), 1032 (April 10), 1033 (April 11), 1034 (April 12), 1035 (April 13), 1036 (April 15),1037 (April 16), 1038 (April 17), 1039 (April 18), 1040 (April 19), 1041 (April 20), 1042 (April 22), 1043 (April 23), 1044 (April 24), 1045 (April 25), 1046 (April 26), 1047 (April 27), 1048 (April 29), 1049 (April 30), 1050 (May 1), 1051 (May 2), 1052 (May 3), 1053 (May 4), 1054 (May 6), 1063 (May 17), 1064 (May 18), 1065 (May 20), 1066 (May 21), 1067 (May 22), 1067 (May 23), 1069 (May 24), 1070 (May 28), 1071 (May 29), 1079 (June 10), 1080 (June 11), 1081 (June 12), 1082 (June 13), 1083 (June 14), 1084 (June 15), 1085 (June 17), 1086 (June 18), 1087 (June 19), 1088 (June 20), 1089 (June 21), 1090 (June 22), 1091 (June 24), 1092 (June 25), 1093 (June 26), 1094 (June 27), 1095 (June 28), in one bound volume
- El Observador Americano, 1816
  El Observador Americano was a weekly publication published by Manuel Antonio Castro, a jurist who advocated judicial reorganization.
  - El Observador Americano, 1816 August 26 - October 14 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Number 2 (August 26), 3 (September 2), 6 (September 23), 7 (September 30), 8 (October 7), 9 (October 14)
- El Oficial del Dia, 1822
  El Oficial del Dia was a weekly publication edited by Cayetano Jose Rodriguez, an Argentine cleric, journalist and poet. He was elected to the Assembly of 1813, the General Constituent Assembly of 1813, and as Buenos Aires representative to the Tucuman Congress of 1815. Rodriguez founded the publication in order to defend the Church from the attacks by El Centinela.
  - El Oficial del Dia, 1822 September 12 - 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Number 6 (September 12), 7 (September 19)
- Quaestiones medicae sortitae et lege praefixo 10 dier. Termino typis mandatae, 1786
  Document on medical issues published in Spain and written in Latin in 1786
  - Quaestiones medicae sortitae et lege praefixo 10 dier. Termino typis mandatae, 1786 (Box 2, Folder 32)